<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Aarti Swaminathan</title>
    <link>https://aarti94.github.io/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://aarti94.github.io/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Aarti Swaminathan</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Mon, 01 Jul 2019 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://aarti94.github.io/img/profilepic</url>
      <title>Aarti Swaminathan</title>
      <link>https://aarti94.github.io/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Incorporating user feedback in the design of a genetics analysis tool: A two-part approach</title>
      <link>https://aarti94.github.io/publication/swaminathan-incorporating-2019/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jul 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://aarti94.github.io/publication/swaminathan-incorporating-2019/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Understanding User Experience: Exploring Participants’ Messages With a Web-Based Behavioral Health Intervention for Adolescents With Chronic Pain</title>
      <link>https://aarti94.github.io/publication/chen-understanding-2019/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Jan 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://aarti94.github.io/publication/chen-understanding-2019/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>UW Medicine-Usability Study for AnalyzeMyVariant</title>
      <link>https://aarti94.github.io/project/analyzemyvariant/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 15 Jun 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://aarti94.github.io/project/analyzemyvariant/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h1 id=&#34;summary&#34;&gt;Summary&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;AnalyzeMyVariant is an online tool to perform cosegregation analysis of genetic
pedigree data. For my Master’s Thesis project, I conducted a study to assess
the usability perceptions of potential users (genetic counselors and
statistical geneticists).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;goal&#34;&gt;Goal&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To assess usability perceptions of AnalyzeMyVariant users.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;industry--audience&#34;&gt;Industry &amp;amp; Audience&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Industry&lt;/em&gt;: Website design; genetics and statistics; usability&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Audience&lt;/em&gt;: Genetic counselors and statistical geneticists&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;constraints&#34;&gt;Constraints&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;None&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;my-role&#34;&gt;My Role&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This was an individual thesis project; I performed all the tasks outlined below.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;process&#34;&gt;Process&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Conducted literature&lt;/strong&gt; review of models of online trust and satisfaction.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Selected constructs&lt;/strong&gt; and framed them into a heirarchy to evaluate usability.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Created survey questions&lt;/strong&gt;, sourced from literature and adapted to this specific
platform to assess each construct.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Built the survey&lt;/strong&gt; in REDCap and &lt;strong&gt;conducted pilot tests&lt;/strong&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Identified potential participant sources&lt;/strong&gt; and drafted recruitment materials.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Conducted follow-up contextual interviews&lt;/strong&gt; with users to better understand context of use
and explore usability issues.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Analysed data using &lt;strong&gt;descriptive statistics&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;qualitative analysis&lt;/strong&gt; in ATLAS.ti.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Presented two potential avenues for redesign&lt;/strong&gt; to client, each targeting a different user base.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;key-insights&#34;&gt;Key Insights&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even though different user groups may have similar levels of familiarity with
the concept and may use the tool for the same general purpose, differing
contexts of use may drastically affect perceptions of usability and desired
changes to the design.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this project, genetic counselors and statistical geneticists were both
target users, as they understood the value of performing cosegregation analysis
on their data and would be interested in using such a tool. Ultimately,
however, their differing clinical vs. research contexts and other features of
their professions led them to want completely different presentations of
results which could not be reconciled. I finally ended up proposing two
potential options for redesign to target the differing needs of these user
groups.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>UW Design Study-Sleep Data for Citizen Science</title>
      <link>https://aarti94.github.io/project/citizenscience/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 15 Mar 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://aarti94.github.io/project/citizenscience/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h1 id=&#34;summary&#34;&gt;Summary&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tracking college students’ sleep patterns can help improve individual
behavioral choices and allows the opportunity to make large scale policy
changes to support students’ needs. I and a partner worked to research, design,
prototype and evaluate an app-based data collection tool for students to
self-report their sleep patterns.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;goal&#34;&gt;Goal&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To research, design, and evaluate an app-based data collection tool to let
students record sleep data, and provide a means to collect crowd-sourced data
for a citizen science project.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;industry--audience&#34;&gt;Industry &amp;amp; Audience&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Industry&lt;/em&gt;: IT; Health management; citizen science&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Audience&lt;/em&gt;: Students at the University of Washington&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;constraints&#34;&gt;Constraints&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We had roughly 8 weeks to do this in, since it was part of required coursework.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We had no prior knowledge of citizen science or sleep-based studies.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;my-role&#34;&gt;My Role&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;One in a team of two.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Conducted half the contextual inquiries&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Helped design the initial layout, and gave design suggestion on first set of prototypes&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Designed and prototyped the layout and interactions for final interactive prototype (in Figma and Adobe XD).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;process&#34;&gt;Process&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Identified and &lt;strong&gt;researched the design space&lt;/strong&gt; of student sleep, potential health effects of lack of sleep, and various other studies designed to collect this type of data.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Conducted &lt;strong&gt;3 contextual inquiries&lt;/strong&gt; with students about their use of sleep trackers, their planning of their schedule, and their use of other apps for health tracking.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Used extensive &lt;strong&gt;literature review&lt;/strong&gt; and contextual inquiries, and &lt;strong&gt;designed initial prototype in Balsamiq&lt;/strong&gt; with validated measures and data collection formats from previous studies.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Conducted &lt;strong&gt;longitudinal quantitative evaluations&lt;/strong&gt; with prospective users to evaluate whether they remembered to submit data each day (using a low-fidelity paper prototype).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Conducted a &lt;strong&gt;focus group session&lt;/strong&gt; with other users, to gauge opinions of different design choices and motivational features.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Modified designs and &lt;strong&gt;created high-fidelity, interactive prototypes&lt;/strong&gt; in Figma and Adobe XD.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Presented entire design project and offered suggestions for future development.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;See the Figma prototype &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.figma.com/proto/Q4SHnpsSaqS7V3lSDjNdfXWw/UW-Sleep?scaling=contain&amp;amp;redirected=1&amp;amp;node-id=1%3A5&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;key-insights&#34;&gt;Key Insights&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When designing a tool to collect data everyday, make everything as automatic as possible.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In an attempt to keep the tool as simple and low-tech as possible, the initial
design to collect sleep data required students to tap a timer ‘on’ as they were
about to go to bed, and ‘off’ as soon as they woke up. But from longitudinal
user evaluations conducted with low-fidelity prototypes, we found users would
almost never remember to do both. Our revamped design recorded periods of phone
inactivity and asked users later in the day whether the recorded period was
correct.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>UW Libraries-Ethnography of Active Learning</title>
      <link>https://aarti94.github.io/project/activelearning/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 15 Dec 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://aarti94.github.io/project/activelearning/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h1 id=&#34;summary&#34;&gt;Summary&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Active Learning Classrooms (ALCs) have the potential to revolutionize the way
classes are taught in a variety of disciplines. While they have been shown to
be effective in promoting better conceptual understanding and retention of
information, it is important to understand how the designs of these classrooms
can affect teaching and learning. I conducted an 8-week fieldwork study within
the Active Learning Classrooms at Odegaard Library to assess the user
experiences of students and instructors using them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;goal&#34;&gt;Goal&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To use fieldwork and ethnographic methods to observe and interview students and
instructors using the space.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To understand students’ and instructors’ use of the space, and identify
challenges and opportunities for future improvement.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;industry--audience&#34;&gt;Industry &amp;amp; Audience&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Industry&lt;/em&gt;: IT; classroom design; user experience&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Audience&lt;/em&gt;: Instructors who conducted classes; students who attended classes and used
the space for informal study after hours&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;constraints&#34;&gt;Constraints&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fieldwork could only be conducted for 8 weeks, the duration of the academic quarter.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;my-role&#34;&gt;My Role&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This was an individual project; I did everything.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;process&#34;&gt;Process&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Acquired background information&lt;/strong&gt; for adminstration about use and features of the space.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Conducted hour-long observations for 8 weeks&lt;/strong&gt; during a regular class and informal study hours.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Wrote up extensive fieldwork notes&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;created visual maps&lt;/strong&gt; of the room layout.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Conducted multiple interviews&lt;/strong&gt; with instructor and students.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Qualitatively analyzed fieldnotes and interview transcripts&lt;/strong&gt; through a process of open coding,
creation of high-level thematic categories and follow-up deductive coding.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Identified areas of challenge and potential improvement&lt;/strong&gt; in the future use of the space as a formal classroom and informal study space.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Provided insight about potential ideas for redesign&lt;/strong&gt; of the library website for the Active Learning Classroom space.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;key-insights&#34;&gt;Key Insights&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Having great tools in a learning space is of no use unless users know they&#39;re there.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most of the students who used the ALCs for informal study were unfamiliar with
the great features of the space, like the ability to connect laptops to the
large TV screens at each table, or the ability to use the walls as whiteboards
to draw on as they studied. In my final report, I proposed adding simple
stickers somewhere visible at each table, directing students to the library
website, where explanations of the space’s features were already available.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Features can sometimes be used for purposes other than what they were
intended for, and that’s not necessarily a bad thing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;360-degree cameras installed in the classroom were originally intended to be
used only for video-conferencing and remote learning purposes. However,
instructors also used them to simply zoom in on themselves as they lectured or
drew on the whiteboard, so that students at the opposite ends of the large room
could see them the instructor on the closest TV screen. In a space designed
with round tables, where students faced each other and the closest TV screen
rather than the front of the room, this was a great idea to help increase
visibility.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Seattle Children&#39;s Hospital-iPad Service Design for Adolescent Care</title>
      <link>https://aarti94.github.io/project/seattlehospital/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 15 Jun 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://aarti94.github.io/project/seattlehospital/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h1 id=&#34;summary&#34;&gt;Summary&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In addition to treating adolescents, doctors at the Division of Adolescent
Medicine in Seattle Children’s Hospital created web-based content to guide
parents in dealing with adolescent issues. I was part of a four-person student
team that helped them come up with a method to make the content available to
parents in the waiting room, via iPads.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;goal&#34;&gt;Goal&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To provide information for parents of teens about common adolescent health
problems and useful resources to deal with them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;industry--audience&#34;&gt;Industry &amp;amp; Audience&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Industry&lt;/em&gt;: Health management; service design&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Audience&lt;/em&gt;: Parents in the Adolescent Medicine Clinic&#39;s waiting room&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;constraints&#34;&gt;Constraints&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Budget constraints, due to a lack of funding for this implementation.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Only 5 iPads available.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Only a few people to manage the implementation: design had to be of restricted burden to stakeholders.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Time constraint: 8 weeks (part of coursework)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;my-role&#34;&gt;My Role&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;One in a team of four.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Led one of the initial interviews; provided support for the rest.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Created one of the personas and participated in brainstorming activities.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Independently brainstormed and developed 3 prototypes for workflow of iPad acquisition and use by parents (team members prototyped other aspects like security and iPad functionality).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Consolidated different features into final design with team.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;process&#34;&gt;Process&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Acquired background understanding of design space&lt;/strong&gt; from key members of clinic team.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Toured the space&lt;/strong&gt;, and &lt;strong&gt;conducted longer interviews with key stakeholders&lt;/strong&gt; such as the the department head, content developer, the administrative manager, and front desk manager.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Created a requirements analysis document and &lt;strong&gt;identified design goals&lt;/strong&gt;.
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Created personas&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;models&lt;/strong&gt; to understand the design space.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Create multiple design ideas for each aspect&lt;/strong&gt; of the implementation: iPad functionality, security options, workflow, and evaluation.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Selected two holistic design ideas&lt;/strong&gt; to present to the client.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Presented our findings and design ideas to the stakeholders&lt;/strong&gt; in the Division of Adolescent Medicine, along with our scheme for evaluating usability, once the implementation was in place.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;key-insights&#34;&gt;Key Insights&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Use of models, like use case and cultural models, can really help to define the
design constraints and understand limitations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While the concept of this design (to deliver adolescent healthcare information
and tips to parents) would be of great use to the intended users, this project
did not have a lot of funding, tools or personnel available to dedicate to the
delivery of this service. By using interviews to build up various models of the
space, we were able to understand these limitations and design low-maintenance
designs around these considerations.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
